Some massive companies are set to go
public very soon. Private companies like
SpaceX, OpenAI, and Anthropic would rank
among the largest companies if they went
public, and index funds would be forced
to buy their stock. That means that if
you are an index fund investor, you may
soon be investing in these companies,
whether you like it or not. The problem
is that most IPOs are terrible
investments, and these ones in
particular raise some questions. I'm Ben
Felix, Chief Investment Officer at PWL
Capital, and I'm going to tell you what
the upcoming mega IPOs mean for you and
your portfolio.
In this video, I'm going to take you
through how stock indices and the index
funds tracking them include IPOs, how
this might affect index fund returns,
and what you can do about it. I'll also
cover whether index fund investors are
missing out on private market returns,
which is a common perception based on
companies staying private longer. Index
funds are generally great investments
because they roughly deliver the returns
that the public stock market has to
offer. Since their primary role is
representing the stock market, some
stock indices aim to include new IPOs
soon after the company goes public. This
makes sense for the purpose of
representing the public stock market,
but the problem for index fund investors
is that IPOs have had historically
terrible returns. I'll come back to that
point later. Index funds today control
trillions of dollars. So, if you're a
new company listing on the stock market
or an investment bank facilitating an
IPO, getting the stock included in a
major index or multiple indices can mean
huge investment dollars flowing into its
shares on the public market as index
funds are forced to buy, giving sellers
liquidity, and pushing up the share
price. This makes index inclusion very
desirable for shareholders of the newly
listed company, but probably not so much
for the index fund investors who are
left holding the bag. And it is often a
bag that they're left holding. Companies
tend to go public when they think they
can sell their stock at a high price,
meaning the moment you can buy their
stock on the secondary market is
precisely when the insiders believe it's
overvalued or at least nicely valued. If
you're an investor, you probably don't
want to buy an overpriced stock, but
index funds don't have that kind of
discretion. They're forced to gobble up
whatever is included in the index
regardless of its price.
The IPO inclusion rules vary across
indices. For example, as of right now,
the S&P 500 requires a stock to have
been trading on a public exchange for 12
months before inclusion, while the S&P
Total Market Index allows for inclusion
within 5 days for stocks that meet
certain criteria. This is called fast
track entry, which is important to
understand. Basically, stocks that meet
certain criteria can be eligible for
near immediate inclusion in some total
market indices. As I mentioned, the S&P
500 has historically required shares to
trade for a year before inclusion, but
as reported by Bloomberg, S&P may be
considering an S&P 500 rule change to
accelerate the inclusion of mega IPOs
like SpaceX.
Nasdaq is considering similar changes
for the Nasdaq 100 to accelerate
inclusion. The implications here for
index fund investors are important. A
2025 paper looks at how fast track entry
into CRSP, that's Center for Research in
Security Prices, indices affect stock
returns and IPO deal structure. VTI, for
example, at a large ETF, tracks the CRSP
US Total Market Index. CRSP adds
eligible securities to the index within
as few as 5 days for fast track entry.
The authors of this paper show that
expected index investor demand for IPO
shares causes fast track IPOs to
outperform their non-fast track
counterparts by over five percentage
points following their listing. This
outperformance peaks at the index
inclusion date and reverts significantly
within 2 weeks thereafter. Basically,
index funds are being front-run by
intermediaries like hedge funds who know
that index funds are going to be buying
the shares once they become eligible for
index inclusion, and then the index
funds end up holding the shares as they
revert back down closer to their IPO
price. The authors call this a shadow
tax largely paid by index fund
investors. It's like ticket scalpers for
concerts and sports events. Another
important index definition that's
proving to be relevant to mega IPOs is
the concept of free float. Free float is
the proportion of a company's shares
that are available for purchase in the
public equity market. Most major indices
have a minimum float requirement and
weight stocks by their public float. A
company could go public while only
making a small portion of their overall
market capitalization freely available
on the public exchange. This would be
referred to as a low float IPO. As
reported by the Financial Times, SpaceX
plans to float less than 5% of its
equity, much lower than the average IPO.
With a $1.75 trillion valuation, but
only a 5% float, most indices would
weight it at its float of 88 billion,
and many would actually exclude it
altogether. Nasdaq currently has a 10%
minimum float and weight stocks based on
the value of all listed shares of the
company with no regard for free float,
which is unique, but they recently
approved rule changes following a public
consultation to speed up IPO inclusion,
eliminate the low float cutoff, and
introduce a float factor in their
weighting of low float stocks. The
cynical view on this is that Nasdaq is
changing the Nasdaq 100 index rules to
win SpaceX over in an effort to get
their listing on the Nasdaq exchange.
Including them in the index would force
significant index fund buying, which
likely ends up being good for SpaceX,
its early investors, and Nasdaq, but
potentially comes at the expense of
Nasdaq 100 index fund investors.
Some indices like the CRSP US Total
Market Index tracked by VTI continue to
have a low float cutoff of 10% for fast
track entry into the index.
Between inclusion criteria and index
weighting methodologies, there's some
uncertainty about how these mega IPOs
will initially show up in indices, but
there's no question that their listings
will change the public market over time.
That's likely why index providers are
considering making changes to get these
companies represented in their indices.
To reiterate a point from earlier,
indices are meant to represent the stock
market. A blog post from index provider
S&P Global shows that just SpaceX,
OpenAI, and Anthropic would make up 2.9%
of the S&P World Index at their full
market caps. That's almost as much as
Canada. But these numbers assume that
the total market cap of the companies is
included in the index. Since many of
these IPOs are expected to have low
public floats, that should be accounted
for in estimating their market impact.
In another blog post, index provider
MSCI calculated the potential changes to
the MSCI All Country World Investable
Market Index
in the event of some of the largest
private companies going public in 2026.
This was written back in February 2026
when SpaceX had a quaint valuation of
only 800 billion,
but the general points are still
relevant. They ask in the blog post,
"What would happen to the index, to this
world index, if the 10 largest companies
from the MSCI All Country Venture Backed
Private Company Index went public?"
Since the free float at the time of
listing is unknown, they go through a
few scenarios. At a 5% float, only four
of the 10 large private companies would
achieve index inclusion based on MSCI's
inclusion rules. At a 10% float, seven
of the 10 companies would achieve index
inclusion, but not at enormous weights
in the index. While the overall market
weight changes in percentage terms would
not be huge even at a 25% float
scenario, MSCI finds that the dollar
flows, just for funds tracking MSCI
indices, would be huge with newly listed
private companies receiving billions in
investor dollars and the largest
existing public companies seeing
billions in outflows.
These flows are what ultimately matter
to index fund investors who are being
forced to buy shares.
Okay, so index funds, depending on the
rules of the specific indices they
track, may or may not invest in these
mega IPOs. And even if they do, it will
likely be at a weight reflecting their
public float, except for the Nasdaq 100,
which as of recently would use its newly
adopted float factor. An important piece
of understanding this whole situation is
the empirical fact that investing in
IPOs is one of the worst investment
strategies that exists. Before I get to
that though, make sure to subscribe if
you haven't already. I make nerdy
research-driven videos to help you make
more informed financial decisions. Okay,
IPOs tend to have a first day pop where
the price on the public market jumps up
relative to the IPO price, but most
investors don't get the IPO price.
Investing in the shares once they are
listed on the public market, so after
the pop has been rough, to say the
least. The consistent pattern of IPO
underperformance even has a name. It's
the new issues puzzle, coined in a
highly cited 1995 paper, which found
that companies issuing stock from 1970
to 1990 tended to be poor investments.
The paper finds that investors in IPOs
receive average returns of only 5% per
year, while similar listed firms
returned 12% over the same period. The
paper notes that to achieve the same
wealth 5 years later, an investor would
have had to put 44% more money into the
new issues in the sample than into
established firms of the same size. A
more recent 2019 study from Dimensional
Fund Advisors looked at the first year
secondary market performance of more
than 6,000 IPOs from 1991 to 2018 and
found that a portfolio of IPOs generally
underperformed the market and a small
cap index by about 2% per year. The main
exception to this finding was in the
1992 to 2000 period when the IPO
portfolio outperformed the small cap
index by about 1.1% annually, mainly due
to IPOs consisting of small tech
companies that took off in the dot com
boom. And I mean, we all know what
happened after that.
The study found that these poor returns
were largely explained by the factors in
the Fama and French five-factor asset
pricing model. The IPO portfolio behaves
like a portfolio of small growth, low
profitability, high investment stocks,
also known as junk or small crap growth.
These types of stocks are more volatile
and tend to lag behind the broader
market. We don't even need these papers
though. These findings are easy for
anyone to replicate and update today
because of course there is an ETF for
IPOs. The Renaissance IPO ETF
exclusively invests in large US IPOs
when they list and then sells the shares
after they've been public for three
years. It has underperformed VTI, which
tracks the total US market, by more than
six percentage points annualized since
inception in October 2013. And as
expected, it behaves like a portfolio of
small stocks with high prices, low
profitability, and aggressive asset
growth. Similar results can be found
internationally since 2014
with the Renaissance International IPO
ETF, IPOS. Yes, that is the real ticker.
Professor Jay Ritter, co-author of the
new issues puzzle, maintains an
up-to-date database of IPO returns in
that data spanning 1980 through 2023,
the average three-year buy and hold
return for IPOs purchased on the
secondary market trails the market by 19
percentage points. Low float IPOs look
particularly bad. Remember, a low float
IPO means that only a small portion of
the company's shares are available for
public trading, which can amplify price
swings because demand is concentrated on
a limited supply. This is widely
expected to be the approach for
companies like OpenAI and SpaceX. Low
float IPOs for high revenue companies
are rare, but they're not totally
unheard of. I reached out to Professor
Ritter, a past guest on my podcast, to
see if he had any data on large
low-float IPOs specifically. He sent me
this table, which you nerds are getting
an exclusive look at. He found 11
low-float, that is below 5% float, IPOs
for companies with inflation-adjusted
trailing 12-month sales of $100 million
or more, going back to 1980.
10 of the 11 IPOs underperformed the
market within 3 years, with average
underperformance of roughly 50% from the
offer price, and over 60% from the
first-day close, suggesting that
constrained supply may drive early price
spikes, but tends to be followed by
significant underperformance.
He also mentioned that these examples
tended to have high price-to-sales
ratios at the time of IPO, which is very
relevant for the current potential mega
IPOs. If SpaceX were to achieve a $1.75
trillion valuation, it would have a
price-to-sales ratio of more than 100
times based on trailing sales. For
context, the highest price-to-sales
ratio for an S&P 500 constituent today
is Palantir's 73 times, while the index
as a whole trades at a price-to-sales of
3.1 times. In general, high valuations
are associated with a low expected
future returns. For index fund
investors, this problem is complicated.
When large private companies go public
with high valuations, they change the
landscape of the broader market. In
response, indices must rebalance to
remain reflective of the broader market.
Market-cap-weighted indices must
rebalance in response to stock market
composition changes, which in some cases
can include IPOs. In doing so, index
funds implicitly engage in market
timing. The problem is that it tends to
be really bad market timing. Issuers,
that's like companies listing on the
public market, will generally want to
issue stock when their valuation is
high, when when they believe their
valuation is high, and buy it back when
their valuation is low. Index funds, in
their effort to track the indices that
reflect the market, end up buying high
and selling low. The 2025 paper index
rebalancing and stock market
composition, Do Indexes Time the Market,
estimates that this timing ends up
creating a performance drag of between
47 and 70 basis points per year relative
to a delayed rebalancing approach. In
other words, there is a lasting negative
effect on your portfolio that could have
been avoided had your index fund
prioritized expected returns rather than
tracking error to its index. Listen, I'm
a huge fan of index funds, but this
issue right here is one of the reasons
that I don't use them personally or for
the clients of PWL Capital. I use funds
from Dimensional Fund Advisors, which
are a lot like index funds, but don't
track an index and intentionally avoid
investing in IPOs for about a year after
the company lists. They also
intentionally tilt away from the the
junk that IPOs tend to behave like more
generally. To be clear, my firm PWL
Capital does use Dimensional funds, but
I was not paid by Dimensional or anyone
else to say this, and I gain nothing
from you using their products.
With companies staying private longer
and going public when they're larger,
the next question that is natural to ask
is whether investors should be seeking
exposure to private company shares
before they go public.
There are a couple of things to think
about here. There's a huge amount of
survivorship bias in private company
outcomes. For every SpaceX or OpenAI
that we hear about, there are thousands
of companies that did not grow or failed
entirely. This skewness exists in public
markets, too, but it's even more brutal,
even more pronounced in private markets.
Additionally, the fees and costs
associated with private company
investments can often absorb the
financial benefits of owning them. This
has been true with private equity funds
in general, which have delivered net of
fee returns in line with public markets.
There are some wild stories floating
around right now about the lengths
people have gone to to buy what they
hope is exposure to companies like
SpaceX. One special purpose vehicle
reported on by Wall Street Journal had a
4% upfront fee with an additional fee of
25% of future profits. There are also
questions about who owns what due to the
complicated structures and of course
there are stories of outright fraud. I
think people imagine all the money they
will make if they can buy some SpaceX
shares at a low valuation and then sell
when it goes public, but unless you're
an employee or otherwise have direct
access to the company's shares,
financial intermediaries that do have
access are not typically going to give
you access to the equity on terms that
are better for you than they are for the
intermediary. Financial intermediaries
don't tend to be in the business of
giving you money for free.
Some ETFs have gotten exposure to SpaceX
shares either directly or through
special purpose vehicles. One example
that has attracted a lot of attention is
the ER Shares Private Public Crossover
ETF. It bought into SpaceX through an
SPV in December 2024. SPVs are not
particularly liquid, so this ETF has had
to deal with some unique practical
issues as a liquid ETF holding a large
stake in an illiquid asset. But even
more interesting, to me at least, is
that despite SpaceX reportedly rising in
value substantially since this ETF
invested in it back in December 2024,
the fund has lost money in absolute
terms and even more so relative to the
market. There are multiple reasons for
this and it gets complicated quickly,
and that's part of the problem. As Jeff
Tack, managing director for Morningstar
Research Services, widely noted in his
analysis of XOVR, when it comes to
investing, the more you covet something,
the more you should probably question
your desire to own it in the first
place. Investors are so eager to get a
piece of SpaceX that, at least in this
case, they got burned. Some good news is
that while it's generally difficult to
get access to the private company shares
that you really want, a lot of public
companies make strategic investments
into private companies. Public market
investors are not entirely locked out of
private markets. Okay, what does all
this mean for you, the index fund
investor? Yes, it's possible that these
upcoming mega IPOs will affect market
indices and the index funds tracking
them, especially if these companies are
fast-tracked for index inclusion.
Due to index fund mechanics, index funds
will buy up IPO shares that are included
in the index at any price leading to
adverse selection and potentially even
making the problem worse for themselves
as they bid the price of the stocks up.
If you're an index fund investor
already, this is a cost you have been
paying, an implicit cost. Maybe these
cases are a bit more extreme, but this
is part of the indexing lifestyle. You
can either accept it and carry on or
look at alternatives like Dimensional
funds that are similarly low-cost and
broadly diversified, but don't auto
invest in IPOs.
No, you probably can't get access to
these private company shares prior to
their IPOs.
When everyone wants to buy something,
either its price or the cost of
accessing it will absorb a huge portion
of the benefit you think you're going to
get from investing in it. If you're
interested in learning more about how
poorly IPOs perform, click here. Or if
you're interested in learning about why
PWL Capital uses Dimensional funds to
construct client portfolios, you can
click right here.